<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Notes on Data Science - Machine Learning</title><link href="https://stefanschmidt.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://stefanschmidt.github.io/feeds/machine-learning.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://stefanschmidt.github.io/</id><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Linear oscillatory state-space models</title><link href="https://stefanschmidt.github.io/linear-oscillatory-state-space-models.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Stefan</name></author><id>tag:stefanschmidt.github.io,2024-05-14:/linear-oscillatory-state-space-models.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A common critique of machine learning research is that the results of many papers are based on trial-and-error, often representing only minor modifications of existing approaches and without any proper justification of the design decisions. The typical justification for publication is that a model resulted in a good score on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A common critique of machine learning research is that the results of many papers are based on trial-and-error, often representing only minor modifications of existing approaches and without any proper justification of the design decisions. The typical justification for publication is that a model resulted in a good score on some established benchmark, with the &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00561"&gt;validity of these benchmarks&lt;/a&gt; being a topic on its own. Even from an engineering perspective this is obviously highly undesirable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was therefore very delighted by a preliminary reading of &lt;a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=GRMfXcAAFh"&gt;Linear oscillatory state-space models&lt;/a&gt; presented by T. Konstantin Rusch and Daniela Rus at ICLR 2025. This publication combines several desirable qualities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is based on a justified theoretical model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The approach strongly inspired by physics and neurobiology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It exercises mathematical rigour&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It includes empirical evidence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It provides a reference implementation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The approach could have substantial impact in multiple domains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is actually an enjoyable read!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving aside the formal perspective, the ability to model very long-range interactions on multivariate sequences with high accuracy using a theoretically well-grounded model makes the publication appealing especially for domains where explainability is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1. I have not verified the claims, but as opposed to theoretical contributions in other publications, given sufficient time the proofs actually appear rather digestable mainly drawing from Calculus and Linear Algebra&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Machine Learning"></category></entry></feed>